George Middleton Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Business Correspondence, 1903-1967 (Box 18-23)
  Letters received and copies of letters sent, contracts and copyright records, programs and publicity for plays, notes, printed material, and newspaper clippings.
  Arranged in three sections by name of agents and individuals and by titles of plays.
  - Agent, Harold Freedman (Box 18)
    - Early records of places plays were sent, 1938
    - Letters, 1933-1967, (9 folders)
    - List of plays handled
    - Prisoner of Fame, correspondence, 1938-1937
  - French, Samuel, business records, 1917-1962, (2 folders)
  - American Play Co. (Box 19)
    - Correspondence
      - Adam and Eva, Polly With a Past, and Cave Girl, 1922
      - The Big Pond, 1919-1921
      - The House of a Thousand Candles, 1907-1940
    - List of plays controlled by the company
  - Belasco, David
    - Belasco-Roeder correspondence concerning French adaptations
    - Colton, Ed, correspondence
    - Georgina, contract
    - L'Avocat, adaptation contract
    - L'Heure de Berger, adaptation contract
    - Personal correspondence, 1914-1953
    - Plays Produced Under the Stage Direction of David Belasco (New York: 1925 )
    - Polly With a Past
      - Amateur rights and arrangement with Samuel French concerning royalties in England
      - Belasco-Roeder business correspondence, 1917-1929
      - Contracts and correspondence
        - Copyright records
        - Foreign, 1918-1949
        - General, 1917-1929
        - Hammerstein, Arthur, 1926
      - Original notes for play
      - Programs and publicity
    - Une Petite Main Qui Se Place, contracts and correspondence
    - Vera Baghdad, adaptation contract and correspondence
  - Bobbs-Merrill, correspondence, 1925-1957
  - Century Play Co., correspondence, 1924-1948
  - Bolton, Guy (Box 20)
    - Correspondence, 1914-1967, (8 folders)
    - Draft of plot for collaboration
  - Business letters
    - Miscellaneous, 1915-1950
    - Rejections, 1903-1961
  - Cohan and Harris, option on plays to be written
  - Stevens, Roger, correspondence, 1954-1965
  - Whitehead, Robert, correspondence, 1959-1964
  - Adam and Eva (Box 21)
    - Contracts, 1917-1928
    - Correspondence
      - Amateur and film rights
      - Kern, Jerome, correspondence concerning, 1927-1928
      - Miscellaneous, 1919-1947
      - Turner, Paul, 1920-1922
  - The Big Pond
    - Contracts, 1928-1958
    - Correspondence, 1959-1967, (4 folders)
  - Blood Money (Box 22)
    - Colton, Ed, correspondence, 1961
    - Contracts and related correspondence
  - The Bride, contracts and related correspondence, 1923, 1952
  - The Cave Girl
    - Contracts and related correspondence, 1919-1947
    - Original text as produced by Cohan and Harris
  - The Light of the World
    - Contracts and related correspondence, 1918-1959
    - Version performed at L'Odeon in Paris
  - Madame Capet
    - Adaptation as produced
    - Correspondence, 1938
    - French text and Middleton's adaptation
  - Diana Does It (Box 23)
    - Contracts, copyright history, and correspondence, 1940-1962
    - Revised and final copies of text
    - Revised script before typing
  - Nowadays, copyright, production and publication contracts, and related correspondence, 1913-1919
- Subject File, 1901-1967 (Box 24-36)
  Correspondence, reports, memoranda, manuscripts, printed matter, newspaper clippings, drafts of writings, contracts, certificates of award, and bound volumes.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Columbia University, New York, N.Y., alumni register, biographical material on Middleton (Box 24)
  - Copyright legislation
    - Articles related to copyright legislation
    - Copyright law revision hearings, 1965
    - Material on copyrights, 1967
    - Universal Copyright Convention, 1955
  - Copyrights
    - Newspaper clippings, 1962, etc.
    - Odds and Ends, copyright
    - One-act play copyrights and contracts
    - Records of unproduced plays
    - That Was Balzac
  - Dramatists Guild
    - Articles
    - Material used in autobiography
    - Speech of Bronson Howard, 1901
    - Chronological file
      - 1920-1928, (7 folders)
      - 1928-1960, (18 folders) (Box 25)
      - 1955-1966, (15 folders) (Box 26)
    - Middleton's literary properties, 1965 (Box 27)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1959
    - Correspondence
      - 1920-1965, (15 folders)
      - 1966-1967, (2 folders) (Box 28)
    - Authors Guild Bulletin, 1956-1967, (12 folders)
    - The American Writer, vols. 1-3, 1952-1954 (Box 29)
    - Authors League Bulletin and other Authors League publications
    - Dramatists Guild Fund, bylaws
    - Dramatists Guild Quarterly, 1964-1967, (4 folders)
    - Dramatists Bulletin, 1960-1964 (ring-binder notebook)
    - Ferrer, Jose, Justice Department brief concerning tax case, 1961 (Box 30)
    - Miscellany, (6 folders)
  - Dutch Treat Club, history by Will Irwin (1943), correspondence, 1944-1964 (Box 31)
  - Film contracts
    - Correspondence, miscellaneous, 1919-1942
    - Dealing with plays produced
    - Famous Players, American Cinema Corp.
    - Fox Film Corp.
    - Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer, correspondence, 1924-1944
    - Paramount Films (Famous Players, Lasky, etc.), correspondence, 1917-1943
  - Libraries having copies of Middleton's plays and autobiography (Box 32)
  - Library of Congress
  - Literary properties, list
  - Medical data
  - Middleton's "Index"
    - Drafts
    - Extra copies
  - Obituaries, friends and associates
  - Office of Alien Property (Box 33)
    - Awards and related correspondence
    - Certificate of sustained merit award and related correspondence, 1957
    - Chart on rights of foreign composers
    - Civil Service records and ratings, 1942-1958
    - Correspondence with Dallas Townsend, Herbert Brownell, and William P. Rogers
    - Letters to Middleton concerning article "Rights and Royalties of Foreign Authors and Composers in War Time"
    - Mayerling case
    - New York Times article concerning copyright program
    - Office of Alien Property, statement of policy
    - "Permission to print" letters
    - Retirement, letters of commendation, 1942-1960
    - Staff and official correspondence, 1942-1964
    - Articles (Box 34)
      - Atlantic Monthly, correspondence
      - Clippings and comments
      - Copyright Bulletin, correspondence, 1962
      - Correspondence
      - Duplicate copies of articles
      - New Republic, correspondence and revisions
      - Various articles, letters of rejection, etc.
    - Copyrights and music
  - The Players (Box 35)
    - Articles
      - Miscellaneous
      - Players' Bulletin
    - Correspondence and memorabilia, 1947-1967
    - Gielgud, John, dinner, 1936
    - Middleton's founder's night address and related correspondence, 1957
    - Newspaper clippings and material relating to 1918 incident involving the Players
    - Personal letters to board and gifts
    - Pipe nights, programs and correspondence
    - Portrait of Middleton by Gordon Stevenson, correspondence, 1966-1967
    - Programs, 1928-1941
    - The Players' Bulletin, 1942-1967 (Box 36)
    - The Players' Book; A Half-Century of Fact, Feeling, Fun and Folklore, 1938
    - The Players; Occasional Pieces, by John S. Phillips
    - The Players, 1955
  - Who's Who, 1949
  - Who's Who in Columbia, 1966
  - Who's Who in the American Theatre, material, drafts, correspondence, 1964-1965
- Literary Manuscripts, 1874-1963 (Box 37-70)
  Notes, scenarios, drafts, manuscripts, typescripts reviewer's copies, printed material, correspondence, newspaper clippings and magazine articles, notebooks, photographs, contracts, and programs.
  Arranged by type of literary work and thereunder by title.
  - These Things Are Mine (Box 37)
    - Carbon copy of manuscript
    - Notes
    - Photo page proofs
    - Reviewer's copy
    - Correspondence (Box 38)
      - Brandt business letters
      - Letters for permission to quote
      - Letters of acknowledgment
      - Publisher's letters
    - Macmillan Co.
      - Business letters, Latham, and the press
      - Correspondence, 1942-1952
    - Original publication acceptance on contract
    - Outline of speech on autobiography
    - Photographs and sketches used, final proofs
    - Publicity
    - Business, debts, souvenirs (Box 39)
    - Early family records
    - Fake telegrams sent on wedding day
    - French lecture notes
    - Grandfather's activity, 1874
    - Map of France
    - Middleton's birth announcement, 1880
    - "Minnie Dale," first attempt at a long play
    - Paris notes and letters, Sorbonne records, 1921
    - Source material, early records
    - State Department, letters and passports, 1920-1927
    - Notes (Box 40)
      - Biographical and plays
      - Photographs for autobiography
    - Record of articles published (ring-binder notebook)
    - Republication
    - Source materials for plays (ring-binder notebook)
    - Columbia University, New York, N.Y. (Box 41)
      - Lecture notebooks, (10 vols.)
      - Yearbook, 1902
    - Records of earnings, notebooks, (3 vols.)
    - Poetry correspondence concerning submitted poems (Box 42)
      - Early efforts at verse
      - Final poems selected for book
      - Poems not included in book
      - Poems read and commented upon by Scudder Middleton
      - "Rhapsody," collected poems (carbon copies)
      - "That Was Himself," collected poems
      - War poems
    - Howe, Marie Jenney, to Middleton, 1911 (Box 43)
    - La Follette, Belle Case, obituary notices and some letters
    - La Follette family
      - Illustration of La Follettes in 1924 campaign
      - La Follette memorial editions of La Follette's Magazine
      - Miscellaneous notes
      - Newspaper clippings
    - La Follette, Fola, "What Money Cannot Buy in Paris"
    - La Follette, Robert M. (1895-1953)
      - Campaign material
      - Memorial address, 1953
    - La Follette, Robert M. (1855-1925), portrait in Senate reception room
    - Middleton, George, miscellany
    - Middleton, George, and Fola La Follette
      - Miscellany
      - Record of activities
    - Middleton, Scudder, poetry
    - National Woman's Party brief
  - That Was Balzac (Box 44)
    - Drafts
      - First typed version
      - Original manuscript (before publication)
      - Printer's copy with prologue and appendix
      - Typed version (contains scene not in printed version)
    - Original scenario with notes
    - Other related materials
    - Research material
    - Correspondence (Box 45)
      - “A-Z” miscellaneous
      - Royce, William Howard
    - Original Balzac letters
    - Reviews, foreign copyrights, and notes
    - Advance publisher's copy (Box 46)
    - Balzac, Honoré de
      - Juvenilia
      - Photographs
      - Printed matter
    - Publicity list
    - Records of the Glorious Company of Balzacians in America
  - Hiss! Boom!! Blah!!! (Box 47)
    - Correspondence, "A-Y" and miscellaneous, (2 folders)
    - French, Samuel, publication contract
    - Original manuscript, 1933
    - Production, University of Iowa, Iowa City, Iowa
    - Published version
    - Articles and lectures (Box 48)
    - H. Holt and Co.
      - Contracts
      - Correspondence
    - Original scripts
    - Programs
    - Titles of plays
      - "Back of the Ballot," script, program, and correspondence
      - "Criminals," production and publication contracts, and correspondence
      - "A Duck's Back," script
      - "The Enemy," script and contract
      - "Gloves and a Woman," script and program
      - "Masks," revised for performance at American University, Washington, D.C., script and correspondence
      - "The Night Watch," original manuscript
      - "Seraphina," script
      - "The Unknown Lady"
        - Publication contract and related correspondence
        - Theatre Magazine, 1924
  - French translations of one-act plays (Box 49)
    - Correspondence with Serruys concerning translation
    - Titles of plays
      - "Cercles"
        - Publicity and programs
        - Script, correspondence, and photographs of productions
      - "L'Homme Maître"
      - "L'Ornière"
      - "La Duperie de la Pitié"
      - "La Lumière du Monde," script
      - "La Maison," script
      - "Le Nœud Noir"
      - "La Possession de L'Enfant"
      - "La Raison"
      - "Masques"
      - "Mères"
      - "Préhistoire"
  - Published plays, (bound volumes) (Box 50)
    - Criminals
    - Embers and Other One-Act Plays
    - Hiss! Boom!! Blah!!!
    - The Light of the World
    - Masks
    - Nowadays
    - Possession
    - The Road Together
    - That Was Balzac
    - Tradition
  - Published plays (in paperback and typescript) (Box 51)
    - Adam and Eva
    - The Big Pond
    - Blood Money
    - The Bride
    - The Cave Girl
    - The Cheat of Pity
    - Embers
    - The Groove
    - Madonna
    - Mothers
    - On Bail
    - Polly with a Past
    - Their Wife
    - Tradition, (2 folders)
    - Waiting
  - Books dramatized and reading versions of various plays (Box 52)
    - Books
      - Barriers Burned Away, by E. P. Roe
      - The House of a Thousand Candles, by Meredith Nicholson
      - The Prodigal Judge, by Vaughan Kester
      - Rosalind at Red Gate, by Meredith Nicholson
    - Plays
      - Back of the Ballot
      - Nowadays
      - Tradition
  - Dramatizations of novels (produced and unproduced) (Box 53)
    - Barriers Burned Away
      - Production contract, publicity, and correspondence
      - Typescript
    - The Cavalier
      - Contract and publicity
      - Prompt copy
    - The House of a Thousand Candles, original typescript
    - The Prodigal Judge
      - Contracts, publicity, and correspondence
      - Typescript
    - Rosalind at Red Gate, typescript, publicity, and correspondence
  - Typescripts of unproduced plays (Box 54)
    - "Devilish Dolly" (Dolly of the Pantiles)
    - "The Future Mrs. Trot"
    - "In Defiance of the King"
    - Letters of agreement concerning "Light Horse Harry," "Dolly of Pantiles," and "Rough Riders"
    - "Light-Horse Harry"
    - "The Rough Riders"
    - "Zermina"
    - "Cavour," correspondence (Box 55)
    - "Crittenoen"
    - "Lord Loveland Discovers America," contract
    - "Parson Kelly"
    - "Up Rose Emily"
      - Correspondence
      - Typescript
    - "The World's Desire," typescript and contract
  - Belasco adaptations and unpublished typescripts (Box 56)
    - "Advocate"
    - "The Desert"
    - "Georgina"
    - "The Other Rose"
    - "She Finds Her Place"
    - "Vera Baghdad," French text and articles
  - Typescripts of produced plays and agreements or production contracts (Box 57)
    - Hit-the-Trail Holliday
      - Contract with George M. Cohan and copy of play as produced
      - Correspondence with Driscoll and Paul O'Brien concerning rights
    - The Road Together
      - Contract, programs, and correspondence
      - Typescript as produced
    - The Sinner, text, contracts, and correspondence
    - What'll You Have
    - A Wife's Strategy, contract and text
  - Working scripts (Box 58)
    - Political play
      - "A Man Who.. .," scenario and notes
      - 1935 version
        - Final draft
        - "Inside Out"
      - 1937 version, "Dark Corners," original revised script
      - 1944, third revision
      - 1945 version and revision, (2 folders) (Box 59)
      - 1954 version, "Turnabout"
      - 1955 version before final typing
      - 1962 version, revisions
      - 1963 version See Container 64, Final copyrighted scripts, "Turnabout"
    - Industrial play (Box 60)
      - "Glass Pockets," scenario and notes
      - 1935
        - First draft
        - Final version
      - 1936 revision
      - 1936-1939 versions
      - 1938 version, "Little Men Jumping"
      - 1939 revision
      - 1945 revision, "She Knew Her Man," original manuscript (Box 61)
      - 1948 version, typescript and manuscript, (2 folders)
      - 1955
        - Final revisions, "Her Great Man"
        - Final typescript See Container 64, Final copyrighted scripts, "Her Great Man"
    - "High Places" (Box 62)
      - Research material, (2 folders)
      - Original manuscript of play, 1937
      - Revised version, 1937
      - Final typed version, 1937
      - Final version
    - Comedy (Box 63)
      - "When Ships Come In," production contracts and pictures of sets for play
      - First version
      - Second version, "The Golden Chariot"
      - Typescript, "No Lady Would"
      - 1959 version, "Somebody Else"
      - Final typed version See Container 64, Final copyrighted scripts, "Somebody Else"
  - Final copyrighted scripts (Box 64)
    - "Her Great Man"
    - "Somebody Else"
    - "Turnabout"
  - Novel, "A Prisoner of Fame," unpublished manuscript and carbon copy (Box 65)
  - Juvenilia (Box 66)
    - College themes, Columbia University, New York, N.Y., 1900-1901
    - Fiction and short sketches
    - Poems, sketches, and dialogues, some before 1900
    - Stories, experiments, and dialogues
    - Stories, some published in college papers
    - Stories and essays, 1894
  - Articles, lectures, stories, and book reviews (Box 67)
    - Articles on theatre
    - Censorship
    - Federal Theatre Project, cavalcade of the theatre, 1938
    - Professional authorship
      - Book, proposed
      - Correspondence and related material
    - Publication of plays, lectures, and articles, notes
    - Speeches and lectures
      - Founder's night address, the Players, 1956
      - Lecture tour, Bermuda and Nassau, Bahamas
      - Outlines
        - Speeches
        - Theatre lectures, includes program and correspondence
      - Speaking engagements, correspondence and contracts
    - Washington activities, Elmer Davis, articles
    - Women, feminism, and suffrage, articles, notes, speeches, Cooper Union
    - Book reviews and articles published in The Bookman (Box 68)
    - Political material, Senate scenes
    - Review of play at London School, 1954
    - "Snap Shots," La Follette's Weekly, 1912-1929
    - Stories
      - Columbia Literary Magazine, 1901-1903, (3 folders)
      - Published in magazines
      - "Stage Struck," original manuscript and text, 1917
      - Unpublished
  - Fox Film Corp. scripts (Box 69)
    - Films under contract in 1916
      - "The Great Star"
      - "The Little Fellow," synoposis
      - "A Wife's Strategy"
    - "In the Dark," synopsis
    - Synopsis of photoplay
    - "A Woman's Honor," 1931
    - "Behind That Curtain," 1929 (Box 70)
    - "Crazy That Way," 1930
    - "Double Cross Roads," 1930
    - "Nix on Dames," 1929
    - "On Your Back," 1930
    - "Once a Sinner," 1930
    - "Play Called Life," 1930
    - "Seven Faces," 1929
- Miscellany, 1898-1967 (Box 71-87)
  Photographs, articles and newspaper clippings, notes, printed material and memorabilia, card index, diplomas, and scrapbooks.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Articles, newspaper clippings, and notes (Box 71)
  - Family photographs
    - Middleton family
    - Middleton, George, and Fola La Follette and others, (5 folders)
    - La Follette family
  - Card index to correspondence, plays, and Balzaciana (Box 72)
  - Balzaciana (Box 73)
  - Balzaciana (Box 74-81)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 82)
    - Articles on theatre in New York Times and Variety, French interviews, publicity and programs
    - Press reviews of published volumes of plays (Box 83)
    - These Things Are Mine, press reviews (Box 84)
    - Suffrage and feminism
    - Eightieth birthday letters, 1960 (Box 85)
      - Vol. 1
      - Vols. 2 and 3 (Box 86)
    - Playbills (Box 87)
- Addition, 1879-1970 (Box 88-93)
  Letters received from and copies of letters sent to family members, friends and associates, printed matter, financial records, newspaper clippings, literary typescripts, and notebooks.
  Arranged according to the series in the main body of the papers, including family correspondence, general correspondence, business correspondence, subject file, and miscellany.
  - Family correspondence (Box 88)
    - Dunphy, Edwin B. and Virginia
    - La Follette, Bronson
    - La Follette, Fola
      - Correspondence
      - Notes
    - Letters from George Middleton to his wife, Fola La Follette
    - Middleton, David and Nadea, and family
    - Middleton, Ida Blakeslee
    - Middleton, Scudder
    - Other members of the Middleton and La Follette families
    - Sucher, Robert La Follette
  - General correspondence
    - A-Z
    - Unidentified
  - Subject file
    - Annuity, hospitalization, and retirement
    - Authors League of America
    - Checkbooks
      - 1960-1961, (2 vols.)
      - 1962-1967 (6 vols). (Box 89)
    - Copyright legislation (Box 90)
    - Copyright Society of the U.S.A.
    - Dramatists Guild
    - Insurance
      - Correspondence
      - Policies and payments
    - La Follette, Rachel Young, last will and testament
    - Leases
    - Library of Congress
    - National Cyclopedia of American Biography
    - The Players
    - "Statement Concerning Administration of Copyright Interests Vested by the Office of Alien Property" (Box 91)
    - Taxes
      - Federal tax returns
      - State and local tax returns
    - Will and testament
  - Speeches and writings
    - Book reviews
    - Contract, Adam and Eva
    - Copyright information
    - Correspondence, 1924-1969, undated
    - Miscellany
    - Promotional literature
    - Royalties
    - Speech
    - Writings
      - Articles
      - Diana Does It, play (Box 92)
      - "The Middle Roads and Other Poems"
      - "A Prisoner of Fame," unpublished novel (typescript)
      - "Rhapsody and Other Poems"
      - Short pieces
  - Miscellany
    - Bank savings book
    - Bills and receipts
    - Biographical notes and sketches
    - Brieux, Eugene, handwritten copy of play "L'Avocat"
    - Cards and invitations
    - Death certificate
    - Marriage certificates
    - Newspaper clippings (Box 93)
    - Notebooks
    - Notes
    - Obituaries
    - Printed matter
    - Scrapbooks, (2 vols.)
Appendix: Note on Middleton's Index
The box numbers that Middleton refers to in his "Index" and annotations were changed when this collection was organized. The following are the relationships between old and new box numbers.
1 Interspersed in Subject File 14A 42 27 48
2 3 15 43 28 49
3 4 15A 71 29 67
3A 5 15B 71 30 67
4 6 16 24 31 68
5 7 16A 25 32 50
6 8 17 26 32A 51
6A 9 17A 27 33 52
7 10 18 28 34 53
7A 11 18A 29 35 54
8 12 18B 30 35A 55
8A 13 19 19 36 56
9 14 20 18 37 57
9A 15 20A 19 & 20 37Extra 58
10 16 20B 20 38 59
10A 17 21 21 38A 60
10B Interspersed by name of writer in General Correspondence 21A 22 39 61
10C 1 22 23 39A 62
11 37 23 31 40 63
12 38 24 44 41 64
13 39 24A 45 42 69
13A 40 25 46 43 70
14 41 25A 73-81 44 65
25B 73-81 45 66
25C 73-81
26 47